Finding Aid for the Peabody Education Fund Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Peabody Education Fund Collection
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0327
5.04 linear feet
Scope and Content Note
The Peabody Education Fund Collection, includes correspondence (1881-1918), subject files pertaining to the establishment and growth of the fund, pamphlets on education, and the proceedings of the trustees (1870-1907). The collection is 4 cubic feet, about half of the collection is correspondence. Major topics of interest include the establishment of the Peabody Education Fund, the early years of the Peabody Normal College/George Peabody College, education, and rural elementary schools.
- Series List
  - Correspondence
    - Abercrombie - Appleton (Box 1, File 1)
    - Archer - Aswell, (1886-1906) (Box 1, File 2)
    - Aswell (1907-1909) - Berry (Box 1, File 3)
    - Bird - Blake Brothers and Co. (Box 1, File 4)
    - Bloomstein - Brunner (Box 1, File 5)
    - Buchanan - Buttrick, (1902-1906) (Box 1, File 6)
    - Buttrick (1907-1914) - Calhoun (Box 1, File 7)
    - Carlisle - Choate, (1893-1906) (Box 1, File 8)
    - Choate, Joseph H., (1907) (Box 1, File 9)
    - Chaote, (1908-Feb 1909) (Box 1, File 10)
    - Choate, (Mar 1909-Dec 1909) (Box 1, File 11)
    - Chaote, (1910-1911) (Box 1, File 12)
    - Choate, (1912-1913) (Box 1, File 13)
    - Choate (1914-1916) - Clarke (Box 1, File 14)
    - (Concerning) Claxton, P.P., (Feb 1901-4 Mar 1901) (Box 1, File 15)
    - (Concerning) Claxton, P.P., (5 Mar 1901-14 Mar 1901) (Box 1, File 16)
    - (Concerning) Claxton, P.P. (15 Mar 1901- May 1901) - Claxton, P.P. (Box 1, File 17)
    - Cleveland - Cooper (Box 1, File 18)
    - Courtnay, W.A., (1888-1893) (Box 1, File 19)
    - Courtnay, W.A., (1894-1900) (Box 1, File 20)
    - Courtnay, W.A., (1901-1905) (Box 1, File 21)
    - Cousins - Curry, J.L.M., (1881-1882) (Box 1, File 12)
    - Curry, J.L.M., (1883-1889) (Box 1, File 23)
    - Curry, J.L.M., (1890-1893) (Box 1, File 24)
    - Curry, J.L.M., (1894-1895) (Box 1, File 25)
    - Curry, J.L.M., (1896-1897) (Box 1, File 26)
    - Curry, J.L.M., (1898-1900) (Box 2, File 1)
    - Curry, J.L.M. (1901-Undated) - Cyrus (Box 2, File 2)
    - Dana - Dickinson, J.M., (1904-1907) (Box 2, File 3)
    - Dickinson, J.M. (1908-1909) - Douglas (Box 2, File 4)
    - Doyne - Dunbar (Box 2, File 5)
    - Easton - Eggleston (Box 2, File 6)
    - Eliot - Evarts, W.B. and Porter (Box 2, File 7)
    - Evarts, Choate, and Sherman - Evarts, W.M. (Box 2, File 8)
    - Evarts, Mary - Fair, R.R. (Box 2, File 9)
    - Fenner, C.E., (1893-1905) (Box 2, File 10)
    - Fenner, C.E. (1906-1911) - Fish (Box 2, File 11)
    - Flisher - Fuller, M.W., (1889-1894) (Box 2, File 12)
    - Fuller, (1895-1903) (Box 2, File 13)
    - Fuller, (1904-Oct 1907) (Box 2, File 14)
    - Fuller, (Nov 1907-1910) (Box 2, File 15)
    - Fulton - Gibson (Box 2, File 16)
    - Gilman, D.C., (1893-1903) (Box 2, File 17)
    - Gilman, D.C., (1904-1907) (Box 2, File 18)
    - Glenn, G.R. - Graves (Box 2, File 19)
    - Green, S.A. - Gunnels, H.C., (1903-1904) (Box 2, File 20)
    - Gunnels, (1905-1907) (Box 2, File 21)
    - Hamilton - Hayes (Box 2, File 22)
    - Henry - Hinds (Box 2, File 23)
    - Hinemon - Hitchcock, Darling, and Co., (1884-1893) (Box 3, File 1)
    - Hitchcock, Darling, and Co., (1894-1907) (Box 3, File 2)
    - Hogg - Jackson (Box 3, File 3)
    - Jenkins, F.W. - Johnson, D.B., (1886-1900) (Box 3, File 4)
    - Johnson, D.B., (1901-1905) (Box 3, File 5)
    - Johnson, D.B., (1906-May 1909) (Box 3, File 6)
    - Johnson, D.B., (Jun 1909-Oct 1911) (Box 3, File 7)
    - Johnson, D.B., (Oct 1911-1912) (Box 3, File 8)
    - Johnson, E.T. - Joyner, (1903-May 1904) (Box 3, File 9)
    - Joyner, (Jun 1904-May 1905) (Box 3, File 10)
    - Joyner, (Jun 1905-Apr 1906) (Box 3, File 11)
    - Joyner (May 1906-1907) - Kelly (Box 3, File 12)
    - Kilpatrick - Kirkland (Box 3, File 13)
    - Lasher - Lawrence, (1907-May 1909) (Box 3, File 14)
    - Lawrence, W., (Jun 1909-Jul 1909) (Box 3, File 15)
    - Lawrence, W., (Aug 1909-Oct 1909) (Box 3, File 16)
    - Lawrence, W., (Oct 1909-Dec 1909) (Box 3, File 17)
    - Lawrence, W., (Jan 1910-Feb 1910) (Box 3, File 18)
    - Lawrence, W., (Mar 1910-Feb 1911) (Box 3, File 19)
    - Lawrence, W., (Mar 1911-Apr 1912) (Box 3, File 20)
    - Lawrence, W., (May 1912-1913) (Box 3, File 21)
    - Lawrence, W., (1914-1917 and Undated) (Box 3, File 22)
    - Lefevre - Lyman (Box 3, File 23)
    - Mallalieu - Martin, (1903-1904) (Box 3, File 24)
    - Martin, (1905-1907) (Box 3, File 25)
    - Mason - Merrill, N.M. (Box 3, File 26)
    - Merritt, (1898-1904) (Box 3, File 27)
    - Merritt, (1905-1906) (Box 3, File 28)
    - Miller, T.C. (Box 3, File 29)
    - Mitchell - J.P. Morgan and Co., (1888-1900) (Box 3, File 30)
    - J.P. Morgan and Co., (1901-1904) (Box 3, File 31)
    - J.P. Morgan and Co., (1905-1912) (Box 4, File 1)
    - J.P. Morgan and Co., (1913) - Neil (Box 4, File 2)
    - Ogden - Olney, R., (1898-Jan 1907) (Box 4, File 3)
    - Olney, R., (Feb 1907-My 1907 (Box 4, File 4)
    - Olney, R., (Jun 1907-Jun 1909) (Box 4, File 5)
    - Olney, R., (Jul 1909-Dec 1909) (Box 4, File 6)
    - Olney, R., (1910-Jan 1911) (Box 4, File 7)
    - Olney, R., (Feb 1911-1912) (Box 4, File 8)
    - Olney, R., (1913-1918) (Box 4, File 9)
    - Orr, E., (1885-1886) (Box 4, File 10)
    - Orr, E., (1887-1888) (Box 4, File 11)
    - Orr, G. - Orr, J. (Box 4, File 12)
    - Osborn - Parkhill (Box 4, File 13)
    - Payne, B.R., (1912) (Box 4, File 14)
    - Payne, B.R., (1913-1916) (Box 4, File 15)
    - Payne, W.H., (1887-1891) (Box 4, File 16)
    - Payne, W.H. (1892-1904) - Payne, W.R., (1891) (Box 4, File 17)
    - Payne, W.R., (1892-1896) (Box 4, File 18)
    - Peabody, E. - Porter, (1887-1901) (Box 4, File 19)
    - Porter, J.D., (1902-1903) (Box 4, File 20)
    - Porter, J.D., (1904-1905) (Box 4, File 21)
    - Porter, J.D., (1906) (Box 4, File 22)
    - Porter, J.D., (1907-1908) (Box 4, File 23)
    - Porter, J.D., (1909-1911) (Box 4, File 24)
    - Powers - Roosevelt, T. (Box 4, File 25)
    - Rose, W., (1904-1908) (Box 4, File 26)
    - Rose, W., (Jan 1909-Jun 1909) (Box 4, File 27)
    - Rose, W., (Jul 1909) (Box 4, File 28)
    - Rose, W., (Aug 1909-Sep 1909) (Box 4, File 29)
    - Rose, W., (Oct 1909-Nov 1909) (Box 4, File 30)
    - Rose, W., (Dec 1909) (Box 4, File 31)
    - Rose, W., (Jan 1910-Aug 1910) (Box 5, File 1)
    - Rose, W., (Sep 1910-Dec 1910) (Box 5, File 2)
    - Rose, W., (1911) (Box 5, File 3)
    - Rose, W., (1912) (Box 5, File 4)
    - Rose, W. (1913-1914) - Russell, O.F. (Box 5, File 5)
    - Safargue - Sears, B. (Box 5, File 6)
    - Shackleford - Sioussa (Box 5, File 7)
    - Sistruck - Smith, B. (Box 5, File 8)
    - Smith, H. (Box 5, File 9)
    - Somerville, H.M. (Box 5, File 10)
    - Southall, J.W. (Box 5, File 11)
    - Stearns, E. (Box 5, File 12)
    - Strong - Tillman (Box 5, File 13)
    - (Concerning) Toney - Toon (Box 5, File 14)
    - Tormey - Turner (Box 5, File 15)
    - Tyler - Vaughan (Box 5, File 16)
    - Vertrees, J., (1907) (Box 5, File 17)
    - Vertrees, J., (1908-1910) (Box 5, File 18)
    - Waite - Washington, B.T., (1889-1905) (Box 5, File 19)
    - Washington, B.T., (1906-1914) (Box 5, File 20)
    - Webster - Wetmore, G.P. (Box 5, File 21)
    - Wetmore, S. - White (Box 5, File 22)
    - Whitfield - Wilson, R.L. (Box 5, File 23)
    - Windsor - Winthrop, G.L. (Box 5, File 24)
    - Winthrop, R.C., (1867-1887) (Box 5, File 25)
    - Winthrop, R.C., (1888) (Box 5, File 26)
    - Winthrop, R.C., (1889) (Box 5, File 27)
    - Winthrop, R.C., (1890-1891) (Box 5, File 28)
    - Winthrop, R.C., (1892-1894) (Box 5, File 29)
    - Wright, C.D. - Wright, G.H. (Box 5, File 30)
  - Subject Files
    - American Freedmen’s Union Commission (Box 6, File 1)
    - Annul Reports (Box 6, File 2)
    - Applications for Presidency, 1910 (Box 6, File 3)
    - Audobon Society (Box 6, File 4)
    - Bass, J.M. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 5)
    - Bonds (Box 6, File 6)
    - Budget, Financial Statements, Etc. (Box 6, File 7)
    - Buildings (Box 6, File 8)
    - Charles Bower Case, 1910 (Box 6, File 9)
    - Charters (Box 6, File 10)
    - Choate, J.H. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 11)
    - College Annual (Box 6, File 12)
    - Committee of Five, 1910 (Box 6, File 13)
    - Committee of Four, 1909 (Box 6, File 14)
    - Committee of Six - Charter, 1909 (Box 6, File 15)
    - Conference for Education in the South (Box 6, File 16)
    - Contributions, 1909-1911 (Box 6, File 17)
    - Cook, J.E. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 18)
    - Deed (Box 6, File 19)
    - Dickinson, J.M. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 20)
    - Dickinson Opinion (Box 6, File 21)
    - Dissolution of the Trust - Discussion (Box 6, File 22)
    - Douglas, W.R. - Evarts, W.M. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 23)
    - Faculty (Box 6, File 24)
    - Fenner, C.A. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 25)
    - Fisk University (Box 6, File 26)
    - Fish, H. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 27)
    - Freedmen’s Aid and Southern Education Society of the Methodist Church (Box 6, File 28)
    - General Information Publications (Box 6, File 29)
    - George Peabody College for Teachers, papers of establishment, 1909 (Box 6, File 30)
    - Getzen, W.T. - Gilman, D.C. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 6, File 31)
    - Harvard University (Box 7, File 1)
    - Johnson, D.B. - Joyner, J. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 2)
    - Knapp Farm (Box 7, File 3)
    - Lasher, R. - Lawrence, W. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 4)
    - Licentiate of Instruction (Box 7, File 5)
    - Little, C.E. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 6)
    - Montgomery Bell Academy (Box 7, File 7)
    - Name of College (Box 7, File 8)
    - Newspaper Clippings Relating to the Establishment of George Peabody College (Box 7, File 9)
    - Olney, R. - Payne, W.R. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 10)
    - Peabody Education Fund -Proceedings (Box 7, File 11)
    - Peabody Education Fund -Proceedings - Publication (Box 7, File 12)
    - Peabody Institute - Baltimore (Box 7, File 13)
    - Peabody Normal College, 1903 (Box 7, File 14)
    - Peabody Trustees Meeting (Box 7, File 15)
    - Porter, J.D. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 16)
    - Property (Box 7, File 17)
    - Report of the General Agent to the Trustees of the Peabody Education Fund (Box 7, File 18)
    - Report to the Treasurer (Box 7, File 19)
    - Report to the Executive Committee-Little (Box 7, File 20)
    - Rose, W. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 21)
    - Salaries (Box 7, File 22)
    - Sears, B. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 23)
    - Southern Education Conference (Box 7, File 24)
    - Stearns, E. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 25)
    - Teachers College, Columbia University (Box 7, File 26)
    - Teachers Retirement Association (Box 7, File 27)
    - Tennessee Central Railroad Company (Box 7, File 28)
    - Tennessee’s Failure to Appropriate $250,000 for College (Box 7, File 29)
    - Tormey, W.J. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 30)
    - Trustees--George Peabody College for Teachers (Box 7, File 31)
    - Tyler, L.G. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 32)
    - Vanderbilt University (Box 7, File 33)
    - Vertrees, J. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 34)
    - W.C.T.U. Settlement School (Box 7, File 35)
    - Waldorf-Astoria Hotel Co. (Box 7, File 36)
    - Winthrop, R.C. (Legal Size Correspondence) (Box 7, File 37)
    - China (Box 8, File 1)
    - India (Box 8, File 2)
    - Alabama (arranged by name of school) (Box 8, File 3)
    - Arkansas (Box 8, File 4)
    - Florida (Box 8, File 5)
    - Georgia (Box 8, File 6)
    - Kentucky (Box 8, File 7)
    - Maryland (Box 8, File 8)
    - Mississippi (Box 8, File 9)
    - Missouri (Box 8, File 10)
    - North Carolina (Box 8, File 11)
    - South Carolina (Box 8, File 12)
    - Tennessee (Box 8, File 13)
    - Texas (Box 8, File 14)
    - Virginia (Box 8, File 15)
    - West Virginia (Box 8, File 16)
    - Unknown Correspondence (much probably from R. Olney) (Box 8, File 17)
    - Unknown Correspondence (much probably from R. Olney) (Box 8, File 18)
    - E. Stearns Scrapbook (newspaper clippings, correspondence from Dr. Sears and R.C. Winthrop) (Box 8, File 19)
  - Pamphlets
    - Conference of the State Supervisors of Rural Schools (Box 9, File 1)
    - Education Campaign in Texas (Box 9, File 2)
    - Georgia- An Act to Revise the School Laws (Box 9, File 3)
    - Georgia- Observations on School Laws (Box 9, File 4)
    - Kentucky- Department of Education Bulletin (Box 9, File 5)
    - Louisiana- Ornamentation of School Grounds (Box 9, File 6)
    - Mississippi- Department of Elementary Rural Schools (Box 9, File 7)
    - North Carolina (Box 9, File 8)
    - North Carolina- Consolidation of Schools and Public Transportation of Pupils (Box 9, File 9)
    - Quarterly Report of the State Supervisors of Rural Schools (Box 9, File 10)
    - Report of Miss Virginia Moore (Box 9, File 11)
    - Reports of Organizers of School Improvement Associations, 30 Jun 1910 (Box 9, File 12)
    - Reports of Organizers of School Improvement Associations, 30 Sep 1910 (Box 9, File 13)
    - Reports of Organizers of School Improvement Associations, 31 Dec 1910 (Box 9, File 14)
    - Reports of Organizers of School Improvement Associations, 31 Mar 1911 (Box 9, File 15)
    - Reports of Organizers of School Improvement Associations, 30 Jun 1911 (Box 9, File 16)
    - Reports of Organizers of School Improvement Associations, 30 Sep 1911 (Box 9, File 17)
    - Reports of Organizers of School Improvement Associations, 31 Mar 1912 (Box 9, File 18)
    - Report of State Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 30 Sep 1911 (Parts I & II) (Box 9, File 19)
    - Report of State Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 30 Sep 1911(Parts III & IV) (Box 9, File 20)
    - Report of State Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools (Box 9, File 21)
    - Report of Supervisor of Colored Rural Elementary Schools (Box 9, File 22)
    - Report of State Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 31 Mar, 1909 (Box 9, File 23)
    - Report of Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 30 Jun 1910 (Box 10, File 1)
    - Report of Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 30 Sep 1910 (Box 10, File 2)
    - Report of Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 31 Dec 1910 (Box 10, File 3)
    - Report of Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 30 Jun 1911 (Box 10, File 4)
    - Report of Supervisors of Rural Elementary Schools, 31 Mar, 1912 (Box 10, File 5)
    - Report of the Conference for Education in Texas (Box 10, File 6)
    - Report of the General Agent to the Trustees, 1907 (Part I & II) (Box 10, File 7)
    - Report of the General Agent to the Trustees, 1910 (Box 10, File 8)
    - Report of the General Agent to the Trustees, 1912 (Box 10, File 9)
    - Report of the General Agent to the Trustees, 1913 (Box 10, File 10)
    - Report of the State Supervisor of Rural Schools, 30 Sep 1912 (Box 10, File 11)
    - Report of the State Supervisor of Rural Schools in North Carolina (Box 10, File 12)
    - Report of the State Supervisor of Rural Schools, 31 Mar, 1911 (Box 10, File 13)
    - South Carolina (Box 10, File 14)
    - South Carolina- A Statement of the Rural School Problem (Box 10, File 15)
    - South Carolina- Clemson Agricultural College (Box 10, File 16)
    - South Carolina- Teacher’s Manual (Box 10, File 17)
    - Supervision of Rural Schools for Negroes [Virginia] (Box 10, File 18)
    - Tennessee- Graded Course of Study for the Elementary Schools (Box 10, File 19)
    - The Work of School Improvement Leagues in Six Southern States (Box 10, File 20)
    - Virginia- A Mill Tax for the Educational System of the State (Box 10, File 21)
    - Virginia- Extension Work of Rural Schools of Rockingham County (Box 10, File 22)
    - Virginia- Literary Societies in the Public Schools- Parliamentary Forms and Rules (Box 10, File 23)
    - West Virginia (Box 10, File 24)
    - West Virginia- District Supervision (Box 10, File 25)
  - Proceedings of the Trustees
    - 15 Feb 1870 (Box 11, File 1)
    - 15 Feb 1871 (Box 11, File 2)
    - 25 Jun 1872 (Box 11, File 3)
    - 16 Jul 1873 (Box 11, File 4)
    - 3 Aug 1876 (Box 11, File 5)
    - 3 Oct 1877 (Box 11, File 6)
    - 2 Oct 1878 (Box 11, File 7)
    - 1 Oct 1879 (Box 11, File 8)
    - 18 Feb 1880 (Box 11, File 9)
    - 2 Feb 1881 (Box 11, File 10)
    - 5 Oct 1881 (Box 11, File 11)
    - 4 Oct 1882 (Box 11, File 12)
    - 3 Oct 1883 (Box 11, File 13)
    - 1 Oct 1884 (Box 11, File 14)
    - 6 Oct 1886 (Box 11, File 15)
    - 3 Oct 1888 (Box 11, File 16)
    - 3 Oct 1889 (Box 11, File 17)
    - 1 Oct 1890 (Box 11, File 18)
    - 7 Oct 1891 (Box 11, File 19)
    - 6 Oct 1893 (Box 11, File 20)
    - 4 Oct 1894 (Box 11, File 21)
    - 7 Oct 1896 (Box 11, File 22)
    - 6 Oct 1897 (Box 11, File 23)
    - 4 Oct 1899 (Box 12, File 1)
    - 3 Oct 1900 (Box 12, File 2)
    - 7 Nov 1901 (Box 12, File 3)
    - 1 Oct 1902 (Box 12, File 4)
    - 29 Jan 1903 (Box 12, File 5)
    - 8 Oct 1903 (Box 12, File 6)
    - 28 Jan 1904 (Box 12, File 7)
    - 2 Nov 1904 (Box 12, File 8)
    - 24 Jan 1905 (Box 12, File 9)
    - 4 Oct 1905 (Box 12, File 10)
    - 3 Oct 1906 (Box 12, File 11)
    - 20 Feb 1907 (Box 12, File 12)
    - 11 Dec 1907 (Box 12, File 13)